Okay. So the the first one is Angutra
1059 and that is Paja Sutra and it goes by
and that is Paja Sutra and it goes by
the Buddha addressing the monks uh
telling them basically how they should
train. Says therefore monks uh this is how you
Says therefore monks uh this is how you
should train. Our mind will be made
familiar with going forth as it is
literally the isness of going forth
and arisen harmful unskilled states will
not seize and take over the mind.
Our mind will be made familiar with the
perception of impermanence.
perception of not self. Our mind will be
made familiar with the perception of the
unattractive. And our mind will be made familiar with
And our mind will be made familiar with
the perception of drawback danger.
Then furthermore, having known the
evenness and unevenness of the world,
our mind will be made familiar with that
perception. Having known the world's
coming to be and its unccoming to be. I
I I stuck with kind of a more well as
literal as possible translation which is
ba va being and non-being. um our mind
will be made familiar with that
perception having known the world's
arising and it's fading away fading out
our mind will be made familiar with that
perception then he goes to say our mind will be
then he goes to say our mind will be
made familiar with the perception of
abandoning or or relinquishment
and then u our mind will be made
familiar with the perception of fading
out dispassion viraa
and uh the final one is our mind will be
made familiar with the perception of
cessation So this is how the monks should train.
So this is how the monks should train.
Then the Buddha repeats that the monk
who trains in these 10 perceptions he he
can expect one of the two fruits
knowledge and realization in this very
life i.e. full enlightenment.
Uh or if there is residue left of some
unspecified subtle too subtle
appropriations he will realize the
fruits of non- returnturning.
So, um,
um,
if you go back to the the beginning, so
like the very first one, it's kind of
obvious, often repeated in other sutras,
but it's it's something that I think
because it's obvious, people would tend
to um fairly often overlook, which is uh
reminding yourself of the values that uh
made you want to practice in the first
place. So uh remind yourself with uh
your own going forth as it is
because um if you do if you don't forget
your own reasons like like your own
aspirations why you want to practice why
you committed to a practice why you're
keeping the precepts why you're doing
everything you're doing for the sake of
practice uh then uh any un unsk
unskillful harmful mental states that
arise is they won't be able to well
completely throw you off the balance,
completely overwhelm the right context.
It's when people take for granted and
kind of forget um drift away from their
own reasons because of which they were
practicing. That's that's how these unh
wholesome states come and uh
person tolerates them, acts out of them
and so on. But if that person were to
remind themselves of their own values
that brought them there at where they
are in terms of practice, they would the
contradiction between their acts of
harmful acts coming out harmful mental
states and their values would be too big
to ignore. So it's through ignoring your
values that contradiction is being
tolerated and that's when people act
unskillfully unh wholesomely even while
deep down or in the broadest sense they
still very much value um their own
practice and freedom from suffering and
everything that Buddha said but then
every now and then when unskilled states
pressure you you sort of give in you
forget because you haven't been
frequently bringing up the perceptions
of your own values because of which you
went forth or you committed to the
practice ractice one way or the other.
So that's the kind of the very first
step. It's really just to remind
yourself of that and not kind of oh I
remind myself and then I don't have to
do it anymore because I know. No, the
point is to go through the through
through that uh recollection of those
things. So to make a point that yes,
yes, I know, but I'm not doing it for
myself. I'm doing it for the mind. I'm
doing it for chit. I'm doing it for the
wild animal.
I'm always reminding it of the same
boundaries of the same context. And if
sometimes those those remindings, those
those those contemplations become say
too mechanical,
you know, you're just slotting into the
patterns of mantra like repeating
because you've been doing it, you have
to stop that and you have to like
refresh it, so to speak. You have to
make it alive. These contemplations
um are not just a um
impersonal theoretical uh uh mental
exercise that you would just be going
through the motions of thinking or
reciting or visualizing. No, you need to
feel you need to feel your own reasons,
your own responsibility for your own
choice for practice, for following the
Buddhist teaching or not.
So when that's always kept alive so to
speak and made um and made kind of uh uh
persistent as a context as a broader
context then as as the very very passage
the same passage says any harmful
unskilled state cannot seize um and take
over the mind. So they can arise, they
can pressure you, they can get closer
and so on. But if the basic foundational
values are something you frequently
recollect upon
uh the mind, the animal cannot be
overwhelmed by those pressures by those
wild tendencies. So that's the first
step really.
Then goes the same like you know the
further refinement it's okay perception
of impermanence.
So it's like
not just what you think impermanence is
but u expanding including everything um
stuff things that are dear to you into
perception of impermanence so that
impermanence is felt again not just
theorized. Um so that's when he said perception of
Um so that's when he said perception of
impermanence refers to those those
levels those personal levels that
directly speak to the chitta directly
speak to the animal. So if you're just
pondering about impermanence like you
know that modern science is proven quote
unquote that's not really the
impermanence. The impermanence is that
which you feel which you feel the the
weight of if it were to change. Um so
you want to find things that that evoke
that and then feed or present those
perceptions to that wild animal at the
right time. Obviously that's why we'll
address it from the following sutas.
Um same goes with the not self as in
like non-ownership
um it's not mine cannot belong to me
again things that are and and you don't
do it necessarily only when things like
bother you and then you just again like
a mantra just say oh it's not mine it's
not mine so to just manage whatever is
bothering you currently no you want to
do it where nothing bothers you you want
to dig up things you want to dig up your
complacencies uh your your uh um gurus
uh your your uh um gurus
layers of your identity and so on. Uh by
the way, this whole thing obviously
applies to somebody who is already a
sapana. So if you're not, you got to
work on seeing the mind. That doesn't
mean that these perceptions cannot be
relatable. But you need to understand
that without uh having uh developed the
right view, you are not seeing the
animal correctly. You have no no sense
as to what the chitta is. You have ideas
that might correspond to some degree or
not, but you you do not have the direct
insight into the phenomenon of chitta
and its characteristics.
So that is an absolute prerequisite for
all of these three sutas we're going to
do today.
So for somebody who's not sodapana, of
course you still go through the same
stuff. Just don't confuse it
for the practice of of of a noble
disciple. But you could certainly strive
through emulate and do these practices
of noble disciples as accurately as
possible without deluding yourself into
thinking what you're not. And that can
actually reveal the chitta closer and so
on. So you should still ponder on the
perception of impermanence. You still
ponder on the perception of not self the
perception of unattractive of the
drawbacks and danger in um well in
ownership in sensuality and everything
else. That is what would reveal the
chitta. So the practice is not
different. It's more like uh the reason
why why why I keep repeating that it
applies only to somebody who who sautana
is because only the sotapana or above
sees their mind correctly
because if you don't know that that is
an absolute requirement for a successful
correct practice on a correct level then
any idea you have or you develop on
account of reading the sutras and
listening to this ajun or that ajan any
idea you develop about impermanence not
self unattractive you think it's what
impermanence is you wouldn't be looking
further because you think well it's
clear so now I'll just contemplate
what's clear to me but the measure of
clarity begins when the mind is seen
so until then any idea you have about
values of going forth impermanence not
self unattractive and so on needs not to
be taken for granted mustn't be taken
for granted
and and that's enough to to prevent you
from being complacent but it's very easy
for people because they become very
familiar to then overlook the fact that
they don't even see the cheetah. They
they're not sure what it is. Again, they
have some ideas, but it's on the level
of theory. There is no direct
recognition and direct communication
through the right means between you and
your own wild animal. That is sorti
basically. Um so the second one is the evenness and
Um so the second one is the evenness and
the unevenness of the world. So people
sometimes get confused with this. I
remember even some translators I think
say it's like justice or injustice in
the world which is absolutely
ridiculous. Like none of these
perceptions have anything to do with
with objects of u of the world or the
world itself. They all have to do with
how they influence the mind.
Well um when when mind is presented with
those perceptions
how does it react to them? So evenness
and unevenness of the world literally
just means like uh balance imbalance
smoothness or roughness whichever way
you want to translate referring to the
the phenomenon of the entire sense
spheres the entire domain which is the
world your own body as as the sense
organs. So in the broadest sense not the
specific this or that thing. So
sometimes that the broadest sense of
your experience the experience of the
world in the widest possible uh context
wise uh can be balanced can be suitable
can be conducive can be calming can be
uh like inspiring even sometimes it
won't be
and that's not up to you. So the
evenness and the unevenness of the world
it's pretty much on the level of bhava
and vibbava of the world. It's pretty
much on the level of coming and going
arising or fading away. So the reason
why it's it's it's it's spoken of in
these general terms is that's what these
phenomena are. If you still think that
the specific things in the world are the
world, you are not seeing the influence
of that broad context of the world that
influence that it has on the mind. So
that's why sense restraint is necessary.
virtue is necessary to to to to move
that threshold and withdraw from that
dependence on specificity of your
sensual object, central perception,
central observations and then the
broader phenomena become apparent and
the broadest phenomena would be pretty
much anything the entire domain of
external which is what stands for the
world. Um and uh sometimes as I said
that might be smooth and agreeable and
balanced but you need to recognize aha
in the broadest sense circumstances are
fine my mind mustn't get complacent
in regard to that level in regard to
that subtle broad almost invisible
context for an untrained mind equally
when that uh equally broad world becomes
uneven becomes disturbing, becomes
rough, whatever. um uh whichever way it
would be manifested specifically through
the uh elements or this or that or um
any sort of border pressure disturbance
that comes from the width of that world
of that phenomenon of the world same aha
now I mustn't let my mind be affected by
that because obviously somebody trains
in regard to those broad factual real
such phen phenomena perceptions of
phenomena of the Anything inferior as
the sutas on those sutas about casinas
for example as they say anything
inferior cannot disturb you. So any
specific thing that comes on account of
an even experience of the entire world
that you are obviously detached from
sufficiently enough anything specific
that comes that cannot bother you
because the framework remains complete
detachment. Same. If you're already not
bothered on account of the roughness and
unevenness of the world,
anything specific that attacks you here
or there cannot disturb the mind anymore
than than than the the broad world would
have tried to disturb it. And the mind
is immovable in regard to it. So it's
kind of an upgrade of these perceptions
of you know that start on that immediate
level. Impermanence not self
unattractive danger. I mean this is also
on the immediate level but in order to
be discerning the actual phenomenon of
the world without falling into
abstraction or theory or um trapped in a
specified sense that needs development
that needs refinement. So even as
unevenness coming to be unccoming to be
pretty much if you train your mind in
regard to those subtle higher
perceptions uh well aranchip or non- returnturn
uh well aranchip or non- returnturn
there cannot be any lower fetterss
remaining really they would have been
addressed with first what four
perceptions um and then same goes perception of
um and then same goes perception of
abandoning fading out is just this again
for most people in the initial stage
those are abstractions uh sessation
letting go. Just let go. Almost like a
poetic inspiration. But for somebody
with the right view, who is seeing the
mind correctly, who has been training
that wild animal correctly on the right
level in that peripheral sphere how we
often talk about uh thoughts of letting
go are actually communicating letting go
to the animal.
For non-sotabana, they don't they just
communicate wishful thinking because
they don't even see they don't even have
the animal there. So uh thoughts of
thoughts of fading out, thoughts of
dispassion, relinquishment, abandoning
are actually speaking to the animal.
So there is no more uh abstraction.
There is no more separation because the
mind is made progressively more and more
pliable, more and more obedient, more
and more receptive to to your own
commands, to your own instructions.
So that pretty much kind of sums up the
suta, which would sum up the entire
training. So it's through feeding the
right perceptions to the mind um that
has been rightly contained through being
established in virtue established in
sense restraint which is what sat is
being correctly established uh then the
mind will have no asas remaining if if
the whole thing is done successfully and
even if you fail to some degree you'll
be at least a non- returnturner
which is pretty good deal.
So uh the second sut is um sitavasa
which is a um a monk's a monk endowed
with six qualities is incapable of
realizing the unified state of cooling
nibbana. So which of the six
So which of the six
says um here monks a monk at a time when
the mind should be restrained or held
back he does not restrain it at a time
the mind should be released or let go or
extended he doesn't do that he doesn't release it
he doesn't do that he doesn't release it
he doesn't let go of it he doesn't let
it go at a time when the mind should be
gladdened or uplifted he doesn't gladden
or uplift it at a time when the mind
should be closely watched with
equinimity uh he doesn't do that.
That person who doesn't do those things
is the one who is inclined to the
inferior to the lower and is the one who
delights in identity and embodiment.
So again this refers to somebody who
sees their mind.
um that is just so much taken for
granted. But the sutas very clearly or every time
But the sutas very clearly or every time
outline the whole um
necessity of chitanita
for sautati sautapati being identical to
the establishment in virtue sense
restraint on account of that you you
discern the signs of mind you withdraw
from the dependence on the sense objects
and so on through knowing your
intentions everything we of we talk
about all the time but see even And if
somebody does that,
yeah, they got the right view. They see
the mind, but the mind still needs
taming. Sure, you caught the animal. You
fenced it off. You got the wild dog in,
but it's still wild.
Automatically won't be as wild as it was
when when it was allowed to roam freely
before, but the tendencies of of its
wilderness and stuff are still there. So
that's the training now. So that's what
Buddha says. one who doesn't uh invest
effort in training this animal
uh doing the right training at the right
time uh releasing restraining gladdening
uh closely watching with neutrality
uh well he's the one who still inclines
towards the inferior i.e towards the
sense objects, senses, sensuality, sense
fears. Uh so that's why he's not doing
the training
u and he's the one who still delights in
identity and whenever sakaya is used
it's it has that sense of embodiment. So
it's not atavada which is what
differentiates a pujana from a sautana
that uh implicit uh deeply kind of
tested ingrained view that sense of self
exist independent of your experience
your sense of self which by default then
projects it independent of the five
aggregates. So that's the puogenous
view. So the banana would have abandoned
that view but he still very much has
that sense of strong strong sense or
depending on you know how undeveloped he
still is can have a strong sense of I am
that is inseparable from the body from
the senses so it's always embodied in
this form that's why the Buddha often
encourage monks to you know be disgusted
with their own body and contemplate and
say like a young man or a woman have a
snake dead snake wrapped around their
neck wouldn't they be disgusted or
repelled with that form so that's how
you should practice to just undermine
any uh lingering sense of uh that
embodied identity to put it that way.
So, or as this suta says, if you invest
the the time in training to restrain the
wild animal that you caught when it's
time to restrain it,
to let it go when it's time to let it
go, allow it to roam about a bit,
to uplift it when it's time to uplift
it, and to watch it with a neutral eye
when it's time to do that. Then you
would be abandoning the inferior, and
you would be uprooting, and you wouldn't
be delighting in embodiment.
of your own you know with your own
senses and so on. So that's why the monk
who hasn't basically abandoned these six
qualities is still incapable of
realizing nibbana. So he might stay sort
of up the whole life but that's because
he's not actually investing effort to
train the animal and that's that was the
case of of many householders who then
due to one reason or the other return
back to the lay life you know after the
Buddha would have instructed them
rightly saw the cheetah trained them uh
they got the right view but then they
were happy with that and you know they
were happy with the fact that their
animals was animal was seen somewhat
contained um
um
free from peril in the future and so on
but they didn't invest the further
effort that could have been invested and
you could have finished the whole thing
once and for all.
Uh so then obviously the rest of the
suta the Buddha goes and repeats uh the
opposite qualities that where the monk
does restrain where he should restrain
and so on and then he realizes nibbana
as a result of it. There's nothing left
for him to tame because the chitta the
animal has been fully um
instructed subdued tamed and then
liberated. in the last um the last suta is the nima
in the last um the last suta is the nima
nimita suta angutra 32
um and says so this is the other sutras
don't specify the the higher mind
training but you could see that uh it
pretty much goes in that direction as I
said like the perception of evenness
unevenness bhava vibbava already starts
pertaining to these low um higher uh
higher fetterss So that's already a form
of adichitta training.
So this suta specifically states that
the monk who wants to develop that
adichitta training the higher mind. So
let alone reminding yourself why you
became a monk and keeping those values
and being established in precepts and
virtue and sense restraint seeing the
basic chitanita and stuff. This is now
like say you've been doing that for a
while and now you're entering a sphere
of this subtle communication where as I
said it's enough for you to think
rightly about relinquishment and the
animal is getting that message it's
relinquishing it's understanding you you
don't need to do more so this suta is
for the monk who is devoted to such
higher mind training and there are three
signs that he should often be brought he
uh that he should bring to his mind from
time to time And you'll see that all
these three signs are quite general
phenomena. They're not specific things
because as I said when it comes to the
adichitta level of communication,
specificity would have been abandoned
long time ago. You are now talking about
general phenomena, accurate perceptions
of general phenomena real as such, which
for most people that still depend on
lower thresholds of specificity
uh would be just abstract. It's just
abstract theorizing. does not stand for
those phenomena. So the three the three
signs the three uh adichita that that
you can talk to your uh animal are from
time to time the steadiness sign should
be brought to mind the energizing sign
should be brought to mind and the
equinimity sign should be brought to
mind. So if a monk who is devoted to a high
So if a monk who is devoted to a high
training exclusively brings his mind
only the steadiness sign then the mind
would become sluggish. If he exclusively
brings only the energizing side the mind
would become agitated.
And if he exclusively brings only the
equinimity sign then the mind would not
become rightly composed rightly balanced
for the understanding the exhaustion of
the uh outflows which basically means
full correct understanding of the asas
which is what really ends them.
But when the mind uh when the monk is
devoted to such u higher mind training
and he brings from time to time the
steadiness sign the energizing sign the
equinimity sign then his chitta his wild
animal well ceases to be wild becomes
pliant workable bright and not brittle.
It becomes rightly composed for the exa
exhaustion of the outflows. And then the
Buddha gives a nice example of the
goldsmith who if we were to only um light coated
who if we were to only um light coated
with furnace mouth having coated the
furnace mouth takes the gold with
tongues and puts into furnace mouth
having placed it there at times heats it
up times he sprinkle it with water and
the time watches it with equinimity. But
if he only does if he only does only one
of these things uh the gold would gold
would either burn or be too hard or
wouldn't mature. But when he does the
right things at the right time, then
that goal becomes completely pliable,
clear of impurities and then he can make
anything he wants out of it. So that's
the whole point of training the mind
because fundamentally the mind doesn't
want to see
the full extent of anonability, the full
extent of the peril of sensuality, the
full extent of the dooka.
And you can't force it. You know, you
can you can you can get a wild dog, you
can teach it tricks, and you can tame it
to some extent, but deep down, it's
still going to remain somewhat uh an
animal. And for those things to be seen
on the level that results in
arahansship, there mustn't be any part
of that animal, any part of that chitta
that is not turned towards it and
accepting it and and seeing through it.
So if there is any holding back means
the mind, the gold is not entirely
pliable. the mind has not been fully
trained and that's the point of this
whole whole suta to explain that for
those residues of of of cravings and as
the right things must be done at the
right time. Um and that will then
eventually bring that mind to full
plability. And then when you direct it
towards the duka towards the full
understanding of freedom and so on well
towards basically
uh having it sink in what you would have
understood as a sautapana already the
way out of suffering the the the full
weight of that to sink in the animal
must actually have have no reservations
towards it not holding back like those
other sutas when they would have
compared an elephant that's being ready
for the battle and then when he's
seemingly trained they would make him
hold something in its trunk and then
they would PO poke it with spears and
stuff to see if it's still going to kind
of flinch back and hide some parts of it
or not or allow everything to be exposed
because it's fearless and it's exactly
the same.
So, and he says yeah he can make any
ornament and it's same for the monk. So
if he does the the the if he brings the
right signs at the right time then uh
whether he wishes uh basically if there
is any opening for any of the superhuman
knowledges if he directs his mind
towards that the mind will get it the
mind will see it the mind will
understand it. Uh fundamentally
obviously the most important one was
when the monk realizes that his mind is
fully pliable he just directs his mind
and says may I having realized the
exhaustion of the old flows enter and
dwell in it. So not just you know
occasionally get a taste from it like a
noble disciple would but enter dwell in
it without a mind ever returning from
that state of coolness. So full
dispassion for that as I said the mind
needs to be fully pliable.
So um that kind of concludes
the three sutas.
Um and let me now just go through some
some questions that I might not have
addressed during this reading.
Um, so
let's just see.
I answer that. I answer that.
I answer that.
Yes. So, a question I got from a few
people. was um
was um
kind of um
what is the measure of this right time,
right tune regarding this last suta?
Um and then also another question was
really about uh people are confused. How
can you be overdoing? How can you be
overdoing the the equinimity?
Um because u well it just seems like if
you look upon everything with equinimity
it would be fine. But really when it
comes to the well the adichittita
training as the suta says
when it says the perceptions of of um
sorry the the nimits of steadying the
animal or the nimas of letting it go
it's what I've been giving talking about
in those examples of um again taming the
animal whether it's the elephant or the
dog whatever you're familiar with
the goal is to train it so you got a
wild animal the goal is to train it the
goal is to make it listen to you so that
you don't have to keep the fences up,
uh, keep the alarms going on, keep the
GPS trackers on and stuff because it
always escapes and stuff like that. So,
initially, of course, you need to trap
the animal like what the suta says. He
traps the elephant and then elephant
shits and pisses and screams and wants
to kill everything that comes near it
because it's tied to a strong post. But
then it comes down and when it comes
down that's when you start to approach
it. So for somebody who hasn't been
restrained any form of restraint
especially when they hear about eight
precepts their mind will be urinating
and defecating and screaming at them to
not do it and they'll try and f to find
any reason so that they don't have to do
it and still pretend that they're
practicing but deep down they know
practice begins with trapping the animal
and for that most of the animals won't
be happy about at least initially.
But once that is done
u you would realize because initially
when you hear that from a non from the
position of non-restraint you think that
the entire practice all the way to
nibbana is just about saying no to
everything. It's just about t tying the
animal down and choking it down and
keeping it down and whenever he wants to
move you quickly restrain but it's like
well no that would just asphixiate the
animal. You're still not going to train
it. That is pretty much the
self-motification. Um so initially it might feel like that.
Um so initially it might feel like that.
You put that aside. Put that fear aside.
Start doing it. And then you realize
okay so the animal is not as wild does
not want to go as far. I need to let it
move a bit within this confined safe say
fenced off area. I need to let it move
because I actually need to learn how to
communicate to it and it needs to learn
how to listen to me. If all I'm doing is
just keeping it down, then not even
allowing it to walk on the leash, like
the only message it's getting from me is
no, no, no. Which means just it's not
going to give up its resistance. It
might be subdued and you know lose the
will to live, but it won't learn for
itself. And that's the point. So when
this suta talks about say somebody is
not doing it that blindly anymore,
recognizes there is a balance, there is
space to move. If it's too tight, you
loosen it. If it's too loose, you
tighten it and so on. Um,
the higher training when it says like,
you know, you steady the mind when it
needs steadying. You can think of it
like you have your dog on a leash. It's
already somewhat trained, but obviously
it still has triggers. It still has
tendencies. Same like your mind does. So
steadying the mind rightly would be if
say that dog wants to go at something.
You pull the leash and the dog gets the
message like you know before you had to
pull the leash and stomp on the leash
and and and hold it down with your
hands. Now it's not that bad but you
still got to hold the leash because
again deep down there are tendencies in
that animal that are not uprooted and
you would be foolish to completely trust
it. So you hold the leash down when it's
necessary. When the animal wants to go,
you pull the leash, gets the message,
sits down, but you hold the leash. The
second example is uh you you um how does
how does the sutter say?
So the second example you energizing
sign. So say the second example is the
animal doesn't want to move.
So it just doesn't want to move. doesn't
want to go in the direction you you know
it should go because again there are the
perceptions that it needs to become
familiar with because in order to to
train the animal or your mind yourself
out of your triggers you need to like
rightly within the right environment
expose yourself to those things mentally
recognize that perceptions that you
don't want to think about death illness
sickness aging and so on uh the
perception of impermanence like what the
previous suta said so that requires
effort because the enemy female will not
willingly go there. Maybe occasionally,
but generally you need to No, no, come
on. It's time to look at this. It's time
to, you know, go to the go to the to the
different aspects of the training. So,
you still hold the leash and you start
to guide it and then it goes, then it's
fine. If it starts, see, but if all you
do is pull it with the leash wherever
you want it to go, then it's going to
become too agitated and it's be going to
go too far. And same if all you're doing
is holding the leash back whenever it
wants to move regardless of what it is
moving towards then it's going to become
sluggish. It's going to lose to lose uh
the will its will to move towards
anything. So that's like too much
steadiness or too much energy. It's all
measured by the state of the mind not by
what you think steadiness or energy is.
And from that point of view, the
equinimity uh the the sign of equinimity would be
uh the the sign of equinimity would be
when the animal is neither too agitated.
And literally, you could think I don't
know if you ever trained a dog, but
that's exactly how you when you would do
it. When you know the dog is neither too
agitated nor too kind of lazy or just
shut down away from you because you've
been sort of restraining it too much.
when it's kind of there listening to you
with a degree of freedom, you let go of
the leash. That's the equinimity part.
So when it's rightly steady, you let go
of the leash because fundamentally the
point of the entire training is that
animal starts to prefer the right things
that you've been teaching it. That's
when you will be liberated. animal will
be liberated and you will know that it's
liberated when you don't have to be
fabricating it doing it anymore uh
through you know controlling the leash
and so on and from that example you can
also see how it would be sometimes wrong
time to do that. So if the animal is not
quite balanced and you let go of the
leash well it's going to run away into
the directions it shouldn't and then you
have to undo that and bring it back and
restart. So that's how it's not like too
much economy, but it's more like at the
wrong time.
And same if you're restraining the
animal, steadying the leash, pulling it
back when it's not going into anything
unh wholesome, that's at the wrong time.
You're applying the the the certain
sign, well, the correct sign, but at the
wrong time.
uh if you're energizing it where it's
already agitated and you are pulling it
with a leash to move more again sure
it's a useful thing to do sometimes but
not at the wrong time.
So from that point of view you wouldn't
want to just drop the leash every single
time and hope that animal will do the
right thing. No, you need to have
developed everything beforehand and then
you know when there is like less risk.
Same like with a drone like, "Oh, I
could try it now because if it runs, it
won't go too far or this. I could let go
of the leash now." Like just let go of
telling it anything and see where it
goes because you would already be fairly
because you would already be fairly
familiar with its signs and features
that indicate the directions of its
intentions and behavior way before it
even acts.
Like, you know, you get a dog, you never
had any experience with training the
animal, it would be, you know, you need
for it to like jump in rage to realize,
oh, it's angry. Let me pull it back.
But the more familiar you become with
the animal, with the dog, with its signs
and features and little ticks and hints,
you don't even like you would you just
need to look at its eyes, for example,
and you know already like, oh, it's it's
it's wound up. It's going to it's if I
let it now, it will go so far it will
probably attack some something or
somebody. And you could see the same
with the mind. Initially, you needed
like full swings between sensuality,
intense cravings, ill will, hindrances.
But as you start training the animal
rightly, you don't even need to go that far to
you don't even need to go that far to
know that it would go that far. So
little position of the tail posturing
the way it got up the way it looks. It's
like you already know where that would
go. You apply the restraint if that's
what's called for.
So if you are learn to if you have
learned how to see those subtle signs
adichitta level signs uh the higher mind
signs then you would know even more
accurately when it's the uh uh uh most
safe to let go of the leash completely
and that's why that practice of
equinimity as the third sign obviously
requires that development of balance
beforehand like pretty much thoroughly.
Uh, of course you could still like, you
know, make a mistake and leave it, let
go of the leash for too long and then
ignore the signs of the animal, but
that's how you would yourself learn and
become more and more accurate in
training that animal. So, it's
recognizing the little mental
inclinations of your own heart, off your
own that, as I said, the broad kind of
evocative emotional, the broadest
phenomena where it leans to way before
the feeling would have even fully
developed and recognize. Nope, you don't go there.
and recognize. Nope, you don't go there.
If it's nothing unh wholesome, you can
go there. If it's neutral, okay, we're
going there, but together.
So, I will let you go there. I will even
drop the leash if I'm if I'm confident
in your balance, but obviously I will
walk with you. I'm not just letting you
roam completely.
uh and that's that's why I keep saying
to people practically speaking that's
why you always need to well the measure
really of the right direction of the
practice or the wrong direction of the
practice is knowing your intentions in
regard to everything and anything you
want to do and recognizing that there is
never a compromise or the external
allowance that justifies uh that would
justify you not putting those intentions
as the sole factor for deciding whether
your entire projection of
forthcoming actions would be wholesome
or unh wholesome. So you could be doing
what the whole world agrees you should
do. If you are doing it for the from the
intention that's rooted in either greed,
diversion, distraction or any hindrance,
it's unh wholesome. It doesn't matter
how it measures externally.
And same if the whole world agrees you
shouldn't do something because no that's
wrong within the precepts. Obviously, if your
within the precepts. Obviously, if your
intention is correct within the
precepts, then you know it's fine
because I'm not doing it for the wrong
reasons. And that's especially true when
it comes to these views about what
practice is and isn't. Oh, you shouldn't
do that. You know, everybody says, you
know, you can do this, but it's like you
could be doing the right things
externally, but internally for the wrong
reasons. And if no practice tells you
that actually, yeah, you're going to
start wrongly one way or the other. But
if no practice tells you to start
looking at your reasons as the decisive
factor, your thoughts, your intentions,
you're never going to get the practice
kind of uh um picking up on the right
level. Um, and that's that's this whole the
Um, and that's that's this whole the
whole the whole point of this training,
the whole point of this taming would be
that if you start recognizing your own
inclinations, your own intentions, that
is already what animal is is seeing or
pushing for and that's already the
message it's getting through to that
animal. So you don't even, as I said, you don't
So you don't even, as I said, you don't
even need to have the perceptions of
sensuality or the perceptions of ill
will or things like that that would
prompt you. you could already see
slight inclinations on such and such day
towards that or towards this and you
already know where it would lead whether
you encounter the perceptions that will
fuel it further or not it's irrelevant.
So that's why that recognition you you
you you measure what you need to apply
not what you think your duty is to apply
but by what current inclinations mood
that the most general sense the feeling
heart is leaning towards. That's what
your int inclinations would be going
towards. So by recognizing those
inclinations you're already recognizing
the state of the animal.
what is kind of urging you for or
pushing you towards for or trying to get
you to do it for it. So that's why that
that that same recognition of your
intentions kind of can be developed can
well certainly starts from the level of
like a puja pretty much all the way up
to aranchi would be the knowledge of
your intentions and the reasons behind
your actions like what thoughts have you
been willingly accepting fueling uh
inclining towards that would then that
brought your mind to kind of lean in
those directions even more so as a
householder or a monk whenever you want
to do this or that you need to start
looking at those peripheral reasons as
to why I'm doing it. Well, I'm doing it
because everybody says so. No, but why
am I doing it here and now? Oh, I'm
going to a monastery because everybody
says that going to a monastery is a good
thing. It's like, why am I doing it?
Well, I'm doing it because, you know,
it's a big festival and there's going to
be hundreds of people and I'll get to
mingle and meet everybody and feel
justified in socializing and abandoning
my seclusion and enjoying company and
talking every day for a few days and it
will all feel fine because it's, you
know, in the monastery, it's for the
dharma, we're having a big festival and
stuff. It's like none of those reasons
are wholesome. So, you're doing it for
very uh sensual reasons, reasons of
hindrances, reasons of restlessness. All
the externally everybody would be
praising you for it. Wow, you were so
helpful. you were there all the time and
stuff to the point that I was saying
that before to the monks there's even
that sut where says the sapana would not
become an aran would block his own
progress basically by um sleeping too
much working too much talking too much
so not kind of restraining himself in
regard to those things and then the
fourth reason would be getting engaged
uh with uh dealing with like justifiable
right sa issues
and then the Buddha said a monk who
hasn't fulfilled his training should
think thus like when it comes to obviously the
thus like when it comes to obviously the
not not talk too much not sleep too much
not work too much as in like become
completely distracted but when it comes
to the fourth one you know so like there
might be justifiable threats to the sana
to the Buddha sasa to this and that that
monks have to address have to deal with
have to engage with he would still think
hold on there are monks that that in
this assembly that finish their work
there are other hunts
let them deal with it because I still
have the more important work to do. So
even preventing you know sana decline
and and whatnot was not a justification
for abandoning the mental training that
leads to aranchip. When you're in aran
then you can go do what you want because
obviously there will be certain things
you will never able to do again. uh like
like in the sutas, you know, like either
deal with the SA or or just go and roam
around and talk to everybody and
instruct the kings or like that other
Ara, they just built a whole village for
people that built his ki and they were
living off of his support because he was
getting so much support and he did the
work. None of that was a distraction for him.
None of that was a distraction for him.
But until that's the point that that's
developed, every intention matters. So
you might say, well again, you know,
this is a good thing to do. Why am I
doing it? And if you start applying
restraint, letting go, observing with
neutrality on that level of intentions,
you are getting on the level of
adichitta training because obviously in
order to get on that level, you would
have had to been physically withdrawn,
restrained, keeping the precepts for
quite a bits of time. Uh so any kind of
uh u uh wandering off in those u in
those coarsely unh wholesome directions
uh there is lots of space between so you
would see the animal way before it's
fullon in other people's pastures so to
speak. So, so that's that's why it's
like the the whole the whole training of
chitta is measured by the state of
chitta and the state of chitta is
revealed through well obviously
restraint virtue and then knowledge and
and constant reflection on your
intentions uh actions by body speech and mind and
uh actions by body speech and mind and
mentally like what thoughts do you
choose to allow welcome delight in so
that then take hold of your mind even
more you can't prevent them from arising
as the first sut says but you could
certainly make sure you don't lose the
right context that keeps them in the
context. And uh and that's pretty much the
And uh and that's pretty much the
definition of the training. Like there's
nothing else that you can do.